Guide to the Mary Beth Edelson Papers MSS.549
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series I: Professional Activities, 1950-2016 (inclusive); 1970-2016 (bulk); 53.99 Linear Feet in 100 manuscript boxes, 10 flat boxes, 11 oversized flat boxes, and 6 oversized folders
  - Sub-Series I.E: Reviews, Writings, and Interviews, 1950-2016 (inclusive); 1970-2016 (bulk); 10.35 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes and 5 oversized flat boxes
    - Suffragettes to She-Devils: Women's Liberation and Beyond, undated (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Tema Celeste: Contemporary Art Review, 1992, 1998 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Text on Art - Story Boxes, Blood Mysteries, Old/New Myths, undated (Box 59, Folder 6-7)
    - Thoughts - Notes - Old, undated, 1973 (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - Time Capsule (Ana Medieta and Nicole Brown Simpson Masks), undated (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Washington, D.C. - Press Clippings, 1972-1979 (Box 59, Folder 10, Box 111, Folder 9, Box 120, Folder 7)
    - Washington, D.C. - Quilt Project, 1976-1980 (Box 59, Folder 11)
    - Washington, D.C. - Writings & Speeches, 1971-1976 (Box 59, Folder 12)
    - Women Art Magazine - Article about Mary Beth Edelson, 1977-1978 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Women Art Revolution - a film by Lynn Hershman Leeson, 2005-2012 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Women Artists in History: From Antiquity to the 20th Century, 1976-1990 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - "Women's Culture: Renaissance of the Seventies" (Gayle Kimball), 1981 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Writings, 1973-2014 (Box 60, Folder 5-11)
    - Your 5,000 Years Are Up! (Rituals and Works to Celebrate the New Time), undated (Box 61, Folder 1-2)
  - Sub-Series I.F: Thematic Interests, 1972-2013; 1.83 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 2 oversized flat boxes
    Mary Beth Edelson was interested in numerous topics such as spiritualism, art censorship, ancient religions, goddess figures, environmentalism, and feminist actions in the late 20th century – all of which are reflected in this sub-series in the form of essays, articles, notes, and some visual materials.
    - Body Art and Essentialism, undated (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Censorship (In Art), 1992-2003 (Box 61, Folder 4-5)
    - Eco Feminism, 1987, 1991 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Ecology, 1983-1990 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Essentialism & Feminism, 1980-2010 (Box 61, Folder 8-9)
    - Feminism, 1976-1983, 2009, 2011 (Box 61, Folder 10-12, Box 111, Folder 7, Box 120, Folder 2)
    - Goddess and Spirituality, 1974-2009 (Box 62, Box 111, Folder 10)
    - Humor, 1995, 1997 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Kali, undated (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Sheela and Baubo, 2013 (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Women Artists, 1972-2004 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series I.G: Administrative Files, 1960-2016 (inclusive); 1968-2016 (bulk); 9.51 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 4 oversized flat boxes, and 1 oversized folder
    Sub-Series I.G focuses on the logistical and administrative aspects of Mary Beth Edelson's career. This sub-series contains address books, correspondence, art loan negotiation agreements, contracts, collection lists, grant applications, artist residency documents, art installation instructions, Mary Beth Edelson's resumes and biographies, as well as information about her art studio located in New York City's SoHo neighborhood. This sub-series also contains exhibition and event promotional materials including programs, catalogs, invitations, postcards, flyers, and posters.
    Materials have been arranged alphabetically by file title.
    - Address Lists, 1996-2010 (Box 63, Folder 5-6)
    - Alejandro Guzman (Former Assistant), 2010-2011 (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - The Amazing Decade: Women and Performance Art in America 1970-1980 (Memorandum), 1983 (Box 63, Folder 8)
    - Americas - South, Central, Cuba (Memorandum), 1985 (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - Archives, undated (Box 63, Folder 10-11)
    - Art Loan Forms, 1974-1977 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Art Supplies and Services, 2000-2006 (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - Artwork Damanged by Paladium, 1986 (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - Artist Contracts & Legal Related Releases, etc…, 1985-2010 (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Artists - List of Names, circa 1982-1984 (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - Artists Meeting for Social Change, circa 1970s (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - Australia (Memorandum), 2000-2001 (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - Avon Collection, 1996-1997 (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - Bed (Installation Instructions), undated (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Benefits, 1994-2001, 2010 (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Bill Bartman (Art Resources, Inc.), 1996-1998 (Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Bronze Casting (List of Foundries), 2002-2009 (Box 64, Folder 12)
    - Budget Grant, 2000, 2010-2011 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Checklists, 1960-2001 (Box 65, Folder 2-7)
    - Collections, 1961-2003 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Contracts - Artists, 2006-2007 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Copyright, 1966-2000 (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - Academic (Requests, Panels, Lectures, etc…), 1980-1987 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Adelyn D. Breeskin (Curator, National Collection of Fine Arts), 1972 (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - Artist Letters, 1975-1987 (Box 66, Folder 3-5)
    - Correspondence -- Belgium (Shoes), 1994 (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - Benefits, 1985-1987 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - Europe and Elsewhere, 1976-1990 (Box 66, Folder 8-9)
    - Correspondence and Exhibition Promotional Material, 1979-1987, 2002-2003, 2007 (Box 66, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence - Fan Letters (Students, Thank Yous), 1982-1991 (Box 66, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence - General, 1975-2016 (Box 67, Folder 1-7)
    - Correspondence - John Bullard (National Gallery of Art), undated (Box 67, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence - Kay Turner, 1978 (Box 67, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - Nora Hoglinger ("Essay on Artwork from 1970s"), undated (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - Photographers and Videographers, 1977-1987 (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - Washington, D.C., 1970-1975 (Box 68, Folder 1-2)
    - Drawings Lists, circa 1970s-2004 (Box 68, Folder 3)
    - East Villlage & Limbo Lounge, 1984 (Box 68, Folder 4)
    - Editing Video(s), 2010 (Box 68, Folder 5)
    - Europe - Gallery and Travel Lists, 1978-1992, 2002 (Box 68, Folder 6-7)
    - Exhibition -- Administrative Documents, 1980-2014 (Box 68, Folder 8-10, Box 111, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition and Events Promotional Materials, 1968-2016 (Box 69, Folder 1-5, Box 70, Box 71, Folder 1-4)
    - Exhibition and Events Promotional Materials, 1968-2016 (Box 111, Folder 4, Box 120, Folder 3, Flat-file-folder 3 Right)
    - For Transfer Printing - Female Movie Stars & Mary Beth Edelson Name in Reverse, undated (Box 71, Folder 5-6)
    - Galleries in Soho (Manhattan), 1995 (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - General Workshop, Promo, Notes, Proposals, and Schedules - Practical Information, 1982 (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Grants, 1973-2010 (Box 71, Folder 9, Box 72, Folder 1-3)
    - Group Material at Printer & Matter, 1989 (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Indianapolis Artists, 1960-1971 (Box 72, Folder 5, Box 116, Folder 4)
    - Installations Instructions - Wall Paintings, Chiffons, Irons, 1996 (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - International Artist's Contract, 2006 (Box 72, Folder 7-8)
    - Istanbul, Turkey -- Galerist -- Proposal for Group Collaboration, 2014 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Jewelry/Lielin - Memorandum about Replication of "The Altar", 1983-1985 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Kansas City Art Institute - "Women Wage War Against Kansas City's Art Institutions", 1986 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Kentucky -- KMAC Museum (Louisville) -- Negotiation for Exhibition, 2016 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Lists of Performances, Projects, Slides, and Studio Installations, 1983, 2007-2008, 2014 (Box 73, Folder 5-8)
    - Loft Co-Op in New York City, undated (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - Mailing Lists, 2002, 2006 (Box 73, Folder 10-11)
    - Mary Beth Edelson Biographies, 1989-2011 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - Mary Beth Edelson Resumes, 1979-2010 (Box 73, Folder 13, Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Mary Beth Interviews for a New Mate - Performance & Exhibition, Video Information, 1998 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Notes, Addresses, Business Cards, and Essays, undated (Box 74, Folder 3-6, Box 75, Folder 1, Box 110, Folder 18)
    - Old Exhibition Documents, 1983-2012 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Other Artists, 1974-1996, 2007-2008 (Box 75, Folder 3, Box 104, Folder 5-8, Box 110, Folder 19-25)
      These folders contain notes about other artists and colleagues including Amy Lipton, George Maciunas, Ben Forgey, Cynthia Bickley, Italo Scanga, Roy Slade, and Georgia O'Keeffe.
    - Paintings List, 2013 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Permission and Loan Forms, 1996-2010 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Photograph Lists, 1987-2009 (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - Postcards, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Printer for The Art of Mary Beth Edelson Book (Sweden), 2002 (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Price Lists for Mary Beth Edelson's Art, 2011 (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - Professional Contacts, 1968-2002 (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - Proposal to the Beaubourg for Interaction Performative (Box 114, Folder 14)
    - Proposal for Feminist Exhibition, 2002-2003 (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - Proposals, 1997-2001, 2004-2005 (Box 75, Folder 12)
    - Publishers Seeking and Requesting Photographs, 1978-2010 (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
    - Quotes, 1972, 1975, 1987 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Random Studio Documents, 2015-2016 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Reading Lists, 1981, 1993-1999 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Residencies, 1982-2005 (Box 76, Folder 8, Box 111, Folder 7)
    - Sweden - Venues, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - The Suzanne Geiss Company, 2013 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Unfinished Plans for Utopia, undated (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Various People/Notes/Memos, undated (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Wall Paintings List, 1986-1989, 1993, 2006 (Box 77, Folder 5)
- Series II: Women's Action Coalition (WAC), 1988-2003 (inclusive); 1992-1996 (bulk); 4.19 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes and 1 oversized flat box
  This series focuses on Edelson's participation and activism with the Women's Action Coalition (WAC) and Combat Zone: Campaign HQ Against Domestic Violence. WAC was a feminist open-alliance organization founded in New York City in 1992. The organization's mission was to address women's rights issues through direct action. Combat Zone, an affiliate of WAC, was a multifaceted project designed to fight domestic violence. The project provided self defense classes, counseling, workshops about domestic violence, and more. The Combat Zone headquarters also served as an art space and featured some of Mary Beth Edelson's work, including Kali Bobbitt. Materials in this series consist of posters for events and organizations, photographs, flyers, slides, feminist essays, correspondence, press releases, and artwork.
  - Combat Zone: Campaign HQ Against Domestic Violence, 1994 (Box 77, Folder 6)
  - Combat Zone Domestic Violence Poster, 1994 (Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 16)
  - Combat Zone Exhibition Promotional Materials, 1992-1994, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 8-11)
  - Combat Zone Installations, 1994 (Box 104, Folder 9-10, Box 105, Folder 1-3)
  - Combat Zone - Photographs of Women's Hands from Shelters, undated (Box 77, Folder 12)
  - Domestic Violence, undated (Box 77, Folder 13-14, Box 78, Folder 1-3)
  - Just the Facts: Statistics on Domestic Violence (edited by Mary Beth Edelson), 1996 (Box 78, Folder 4)
  - Negatives - Archives WAC at Combat Zone, undated (Box 78, Folder 5)
  - Photographs - Combat Zone Self Defense Workshops, undated (Box 78, Folder 6-9, Box 79, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs - Kali Bobbitt and Space Women from Shelters (Combat Zone), undated (Box 79, Folder 3)
  - Photographs - Out of the Kitchen, undated (Box 79, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - Photos from Mary Beth Edelson, WAC Actions, etc…, undated (Box 79, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs - "We Have What It Takes to Hang In Pace Gallery" Protest, 1992 (Box 79, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Combat Zone: Shoe Town Window, 1995 (Box 79, Folder 8)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Heresies, undated (Box 79, Folder 9-10)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Protests and Activist Groups (includes Yoko Ono), undated (Box 80, Folder 1-5)
  - Photographs and Negatives - "Save Our Cities, Save Our Children" Protest, 1992 (Box 80, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and Negatives - "Stop Rape - Yugoslavia" (March to the United Nations), 1992-1993 (Box 81, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs and Negatives - WAC Democratic Convention (Museum Mile), 1992 (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and Negatives - WAC "March in March", 1994 (Box 81, Folder 4, Box 105)
  - Press, 1992-1997 (Box 81, Folder 5-7)
  - Protests - Martin Luther King Jr. Banner and WAC Chinatown, 1988, 2002 (Box 81, Folder 8, Box 105, Folder 5)
  - Slides - WAC Political Protests, 1991-2000 (Box 81, Folder 9-10)
  - WAC Actions - How to Plan an Action, undated (Box 81, Folder 11)
  - WAC Media Committee - Media Package, Press Release, Media Info, undated (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - WAC - Members Orientation Packet, undated (Box 82, Folder 2)
  - WAC Old Addresses (Names), circa 1993 (Box 82, Folder 3)
  - WAC Stats: The Facts About Women, 1993 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Women's Action Alliance Pins, undated (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Women's Action Coalition (Photographs), undated (Box 82, Folder 6-9, Box 83, Folder 1, Box 105, Folder 6)
  - Women's Action Coalition - Scream Out! (Box 83, Folder 2)
- Series III: A.I.R. Gallery, 1956-2008 (inclusive); 1972-1986 (bulk); 3.25 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, 2 oversized flat boxes, and 2 oversized folders
  Mary Beth Edeslson joined the feminist artist cooperative A.I.R. Gallery (Artists in Residence) in the late 1970s and held exhibitions there including The Memorial to the 9,000,000 Women Burned as Witches in the Christian Era. This series documents Edelson's relationship and participation with the A.I.R. Gallery and contains artwork, slides, correspondence, photographs, press releases, as well as essays written either about A.I.R. Gallery or by members of the organization. This series also contains digital photographs and documents related to the creation of an A.I.R. Gallery book.
  - A.I.R. - 9,000,000, Grapceva,Yugoslavia (Slides), 1977 (Box 105, Folder 7-8)
  - A.I.R. Affiliate Members, undated (Box 83, Folder 3)
  - A.I.R Dupes (Slides) (Box 105, Folder 9)
  - A.I.R. Gallery, 1976-1978, 1983-1984, 2007-2008 (Box 83, Folder 6-7)
  - A.I.R. Gallery Book, 2006-2008; cuid39076 (Box 83, Folder 4-5, 8, Box 115, Folder 16, Box Shared Fales 086, Folder 17, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_549_ER_2)
  - A.I.R. Gallery Monday Nights - Panels, Presentations, Performances, 1979-1983 (Box 83, Folder 9)
  - A.I.R. Gallery Move - 63 Crosby Street, undated (Box 83, Folder 10)
  - A.I.R. Gallery and Other Artists (Slides) (Box 105, Folder 10, Box 106, Folder 1-2)
  - A.I.R. General Information, 1975-1996 (Box 84, Folder 1-4, Box 110, Folder 26)
  - A.I.R. - Press, 1973-1984 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Anne Healy Artwork (Slides), 1974-1981 (Box 106, Folder 3)
  - Clover Vail Artwork (Slides), 1980-1983 (Box 106, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 84, Folder 6)
  - Donna Byars Artwork (Slides), 1976-1981 (Box 106, Folder 5)
  - Dotty Attie Artwork (Slides), undated (Box 106, Folder 6)
  - Elaine Reicher Artwork (Slides), 1981-1984 (Box 106, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition & Events Promotional Materials (Box 84, Folder 7)
  - Giving Myself a 5 Year Retrospective (Slides), circa 1972-1975 (Box 106, Folder 8-9)
  - Harmony Hammond Artwork (Slides), 1971-1981 (Box 106, Folder 10)
  - Larson Slide Sets (Box 84, Folder 8)
  - Lenore Goldberg Artwork (Slides), 1981-1983 (Box 106, Folder 11)
  - Loretta Dunkelman Artwork (Slides), 1973-1982 (Box 106, Folder 12)
  - Louise Kramer Artwork (Slides), 1976, 1979, 1983 (Box 106, Folder 13)
  - Lucy Lippard, 1976, 1983 (Box 84, Folder 9-11)
  - Lunds - Konsthall & A.I.R. Gallery, 1981 (Box 85, Folder 1, Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Mary Beth Edelson Artwork (Slides), 1972-1987 (Box 106, Folder 14)
  - Mary Grigoriadis Artwork (Slides), 1973-1982 (Box 106, Folder 15)
  - Members, Art, & People, undated (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Memorial to 9,000,000 Women Burned as Witches in the Christian Era, 1976-1977, 1986 (Box 85, Folder 3-5, Flat-file-folder 3 Right)
  - Nancy Spero Artwork (Slides), circa 1956-1982 (Box 106, Folder 16)
  - The Nature of Balancing (A.I.R.), 1979 (Box 85, Folder 6, Box 106, Folder 17-18)
  - Notebook - A.I.R. Panel, 1997 (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - One-on-One Program: Daria and Mary Beth, 1984 (Box 85, Folder 8)
  - Sandra Eisenstein Artwork (Slides) (Box 107, Folder 1)
  - Sarah Draney Artwork(Slides) (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Sari Dienes Art, 1983 (Box 85, Folder 9, Box 107, Folder 3)
  - Trickster - A.I.R., Edelson, 1981 (Box 85, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Personal Materials, 1947-2012; 2.98 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 oversized flat box.
  This series focuses on aspects of Edelson's personal life and contains correspondence with her family the Johnsons, as well as materials related to Edelson's alma mater DePauw University, including alumni bulletins featuring articles about her and her college-era sketchbooks. Some materials related to Edelson's personal travels and her anti-war activism can also be found in this series.
  - Address Books, undated, 2002 (Box 85, Folder 11-12)
  - Alumni Art Exhibition Certificate, 1962 (Box 85, Folder 13)
  - The Anvil - Publication for East Chicago Washington High School Alumni Association, 2001-2002 (Box 85, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 85, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Family, 1957-1990 (Box 85, Folder 16-18, Box 86, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence - Old Letters, Indianapolis, 1959-1969 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - DePauw University, 1954-1955, 2002-2004 (Box 86, Folder 4-6, Box 107, Folder 4)
  - Domestic Travels, 1976-2010 (Box 86, Folder 7-11, Box 87, Folder 1-7)
    Materials in these folders relate to Mary Beth's personal travels throughout the United States to Indiana, Florida, Long Island, Maine, Manhattan, the New Jersey Shore, New Orleans, Pennsylvania, San Francisco, and upstate New York.
  - International Travels, 1977-1979, 1987, 2002-2003, 2011, 2014 (Box 87, Folder 8-11)
    Materials in these folders relate to Mary Beth Edelson's personal travels to Brazil, Puerto Rico, Canada, Egypt, and Iceland.
  - Kingston, NY (Edelson's House), 1982-1985 (Box 87, Folder 12)
  - New York University, 1958 (Box 121, Folder 1)
  - News clippings about Mary Lou Johnson (Mother), 1980 (Box 110, Folder 28, Box 115, Folder 17)
  - Papers, 1951-1975 (Box 121, Folder 2)
  - Parties/Social (Guest Lists, Recipes, Menus), 1970-2013 (Box 121, Folder 3)
  - Protesting War, 2002-2004 (Box 121, Folder 4-6, Box 110, Folder 27)
  - Student Era Sketchbooks, 1947-1958 (Box 121, Folder 7-8, Box 122, Folder 1-4)